software engineering radio episode 38
interview with James Noble
[Music]
okay hey this is another episode of
software engineering radio this time we
have James Nobel in the interview and
why don't you start by explaining
something about yourself and what you do
in real life and and so on thank you and
it's great to be here on software
engineering radio what do I do in real
life what I always introduce myself as
being James Nobel and sadly that's like
the virtue but not the prize so if
you're spelling my surname they'll just
just remember that actually that's a bit
that you can cut out you can leave the
virtue but not the prize that cut that
out a little bit louder so that's that's
great
so I should speak a little bit a little
bit louder so I think it would be good
if we have all these comments about the
bits that I should cut out and then you
not cut them out and leave them in the
podcast or I don't need to speak a
little bit louder do I owe it just like
recording on Pro Tools back home which
is which is something I don't spend
enough time doing playing playing
guitars or recording music with the
aspect-oriented Muse durman music
software Ableton Live which reminds us
of reminds us of the fact that we were
still at the AOS D conference in Bonn in
March 2006 and the problem is we don't
have any aspect-oriented topics we talk
about so we should talk about maybe this
postmodern
programming an architecture thing right
well it's funny you you put it that way
because of course one of the the
stranger claims we made in the notes on
postmodern programming myself and my
co-conspirator professor Rob the middle
now at Carleton University claims is
that in fact aspect orientation or
cross-cutting modulus Gregor thinks
we'll try and get him the Nobel Prize
that's probably something you should cut
out
[Laughter]
okay so that the point is that the idea
there is that software needs to be made
up of a whole lot of different concerns
we can't just have a single
decomposition a single you know that the
tyranny of the dominant decomposition a
single idea about the way we design our
software and some of the ideas that
we're linking to both in the philosophy
and the practice of post-modernism
ranging from the French philosopher
javis why leotard writing in the 1960s
just after the riots - you know DJ
Spooky in New York come down to this
idea that there is not really one grand
narrative one big story about the way we
can or we should think about the world
and in the same way aspect orientation
is saying look there's not really one
big way that you should think about your
programs you can't just take a
functional decomposition you can't just
take an object oriented decomposition
you can't just focus on security or on
performance what you somehow have to do
is treat each of those things with the
same the same respect and then listen to
how all these these concerns small
stories little bits in your program
listen to the things they're saying and
watch out about the way when you come to
make a decision the way in which these
little stories push and pull against
each other
so this argues more or less against this
we have this consistent architecture and
this one programming language that can
do also what you're saying is basically
let things grow or or what's there
what's the message well I think the
message is this far is that when you're
making a decision you need to look and
consider all the possible forces that
might be involved in a decision and once
again this is this is something that
comes out very strongly if you look at
design patterns which of course we're
also tiring with the postmodern brush so
you need to look and see what particular
things are impinging upon the particular
decision you have to make and then
making that decision in the light of all
all the knowledge and all the concerns
you have at the particular time bearing
in mind that even in the same program
you may find you've got different
concerns or different forces that you
have to consider and this is once again
where the design patterns are a good
example of this they're not trying to
say something a design of your whole
program they are on one side saying
here's about how you design a micro
architecture a small part of the program
and the same design pattern in the same
program but used in a different place
may actually result in quite a different
design because of the particular
concerns that you're faced with and then
if you scale that up to the whole
process of building software whether
it's the choice of the programming
language whether it's the choice of
architecture whether it's the choice of
IDE whether it's the issues about how
your teams are organized whatever it is
we are saying really the only viable way
we have making these decisions about how
we organize things is you have to be
made locally because the other
postmodern critique is it said ok well
you can insist that everybody is going
to run on one programming language you
can't insist that everything is going to
be done in one way or the other way but
that's not going to give you the best
solution and what you'll find is if you
look for example what your developers
are doing they're always trying to get
out from underneath you know if your IDE
really really only lets you work in a
particular language you'll find
developers will busily write an
interpreter for something else they'd
rather using that language in your fancy
IDE and then they'll be loading up
script files and they'll be doing things
that things that way you know if you
talk about postmodern what is modern you
know I could give you a definition of
post-modernism but we've really only got
about half an hour so it would it would
probably take too long so one of the
definitions of post-modernism i mean
this is where it all kinds of gets
interesting and and self-reflexive which
is something we really like Stephen
Connor for example says post-modernism
is that condition in which for the first
time and as a result of the technologies
which allow the large scale storage
access and reproduction of records of
the past the past appears to be included
in the present ok rephrase that I could
but I'm not going to I mean in the notes
on post-modernism we say modernism or
post modern software practice
simultaneously replace replaces the
software engineering modern software
engineering that went before while
simultaneously fulfilling it
okay so I decide I'm going to do
postmodern software development I'm an
architect on some project with I don't
know ten different developers working in
the typical j2ee or dotnet area
traditional tooling modern in the sense
of I'm using latest technology like
aspectj for example or model development
now I decide I want to be postmodern
what do I do differently well I think
the first thing I would strongly
recommend you do especially if you live
in London is you just you just go to the
pub so for example you could go to the
the old Bank of England on on a Tuesday
night I think that's that's a very good
postmodern moving one which we always
recommend postmodern software
development is about it said this is
this this this this people thing things
should be done so people feel good lying
in the XP and an agile community how is
the relationship to agile development
well I'm of course kind of Claim agile
development as being another
manifestation of some parts of
post-modernism own I don't like saying
this is post-modernism or this isn't
because that's that's just too easy and
it also in some ways I suppose because I
think it's inaccurate but what I'm happy
to say is some parts of this approach
seem to be taking a postmodern thing and
I should mention that modern doesn't
mean today if I want to talk about today
I like the idea of saying contemporary
or saying well software development as
it's being done in 2006 or best practice
in 2006 because I mean if you look at
books in computer science with the name
modern there's this excellent book which
I reckon and everybody needs called
something like modern compiler
construction written in 1968 so in agile
development you know we do find this
once again if you look at the way
leotard the French philosopher describes
modernism as these small literally
describes sorry post-modernism the
leotard and the way decisions are made
the structure of power Foucault the
structure of knowledge is you have a
number of small stories that are brought
into play and when you want to make a
decision you have to make a decision by
considering each of these small stories
on their merits
um at least initially as if none of
these particular stories is more
important than any other or other if
you're going to make these kind of
decisions about importance you're making
them at the time and you're making them
as best you can with the knowledge you
have available which sounds exactly like
what's at the core of XP and the XP
planning game so this is you know this
is one of the interesting things you get
into this in this business where you one
day you're reading you know the Chemex
white book and the next minute you're
reading some obscure absque ruse
abstruse text on some publisher that I
can't even remember the name of and the
things that they're describing are
really very similar another thing that I
remember from reading your paper was but
there are some programming languages
that you consider more postmodern than
others if I get that right I think I
remember that you kind of advocated
using Perl well I'm not really sure I
advocate using anything mainly because
the sponsorship deals that I have are
not sufficiently expensive for me to
advocate things the fact that I've said
that is of course another postmodern
intertextual reference but we'll we can
we can leave it there and my name is
easy to find on the web if you're
interested in those kind of you can put
stuff in the show notes so to make sure
people actually understand that this is
serious and not just a joke well I kind
of disagree with that approach because
you know one of the most beautiful
things I've seen in an art gallery
recently was at the beau Borg in Paris
where there is some next to Marshall
duchamp's fountain sculpture if you know
what this is and that is one of the I
guess what I would claim the modern
postman might probably claim you know
heading towards postmodern Dada art was
Marshall du shams hat rack which looks
absolutely beautiful but is basically a
hat rack hanging in the the gallery with
with a spotlight giving you a shadow
shadow on the wall but I mean if you're
gonna talk about jokes let's go back to
Eric Raymond who apart from his weapons
carrying advocacy activities of late
look up in the hackers dictionary haha
only serious one of the effects you know
in just the same way as if you're going
to mandate everybody programming in Java
and your developers are going to
you know hopefully yeah hopefully in in
sensible ways are going to find out that
it might be better to stick stuff
XML or shell scripts alright in Ruby
alright in Python alright in C then just
use Java there are places where one is
appropriate there are places when others
are appropriate and that's actually a
really good point that people select one
tool and then they do everything with it
and you can see that in all kinds of
areas they have you know they learn Java
they do everything this Java they now
people understand XML is good for
configuration so they write huge amounts
of XML files so the idea of of using the
right tool for the right for the photos
for the suitable purposes it's not
something that many people actually do
because most people can only operate one
or two tools right and that's that's
certainly part of it because in - in two
ways one of which is to come back to
what you're saying earlier about the
situatedness or the you know the fact
that software developers of people
software developers have expertise
they're in teams they've got Team
Dynamics we need to know about these
things and our choice of tools is
neither and uninterested nor a
disinterested one in the sense that you
know the team using the tools this is
going to dictate what they do with a
large portion of their life for the
duration for the duration of a project
it's going to be determined by what tool
they think is going to look best on this
CV to get them the next job it's going
to be determined by the fact that they
happen to know that you know basically
the Java group or the c-sharp group or
whoever has the coolest conferences
where you get to drive around on
motorised toilets I mean all of these
things are important than going to
decision making and at some level I
think you have to take all of these
things what these things on board or you
do take all of these things on board and
the question is you got to be upfront
and say that you do or not in terms of
programming languages I'm Larry wall is
completely out of the closet about this
and claim Perl was the first post modern
programming language and describes why
that quote I read earlier about how one
of the things about post-modernism is
the idea of the present includes the
past in a way which was never really
possible before and you know you can see
this in software engineering like the
ACM digital library every important
paper published by Computer Sciences you
know is now available online in that
sense there's no difference between a
paper written 50 years ago and a paper
written today the same thing is
happening in music the same thing is
happening in our
same thing is happening in TV the same
thing is happening in source code so if
you want to write a program the sensible
way to do it is to go to Google and see
if you can just get the source code
written before and you know you might
want to maybe talk about this one this
episode of writing what was it a sorting
algorithm or something Iram really
important problem in computer science
and and we've got to understand that for
for computer science of a particular
time and place the stuff that I would
generally call modern computer science
the most important problem posed by
Edsger Dijkstra no less is this question
of how do you calculate prime numbers
and so if you read notes on structured
programming which I strongly suggest you
read and in fact there's a sort of as a
sort of side issue if you're going to
read notes on postmodern programming
which is available by your favorite
search engine I've already plugged
Google but since they're not paying me I
should plug Microsoft search as well or
or whatever else you want to use if you
read notes on structured programming
particularly the first book and then go
back and reread the notes on postmodern
programming you'll see that there's a
certain amount of relationship between
the two in particular Dykstra has the
first example of stepwise system
construction where he stresses that the
way to build a software is by taking
requirements and then going top-down
dividing the thing into individual steps
with the same kind of hierarchical
structure in the process that you're
going to get in the structure of Pascal
program or something so we give an
example of the same obviously absolutely
crucial problem for computer science the
task is to instruct a computer to print
a table of the first thousand prime
numbers to being considered the first
prime number and then say you know to
write this program we first connected
out a computer to the internet
downloaded some music from Napster and
read our email you have to receive email
to perform a workday reference 11 which
you can look up and find out why we had
that there this is another one of these
inter textual references we received 25
pieces of email of which 16 were
advertisements for internet pornography
administrivia or invitations to invest
in Nigerian currency trades after
dealing with this email we type to
calculate Prime
numbers into google this found several
websites regarding prime numbers and
other websites and other information as
well which we also processed us
described in the paper if you read on so
the point is here that that is now the
sensible way to write programs it's
getting to the point where if someone
asks you to write a program and you
don't do that that is considered bad
practice now that's not the way I'm
allowed to really teach students in
courses it's probably not the way if you
had a university education they said
okay here's an example you've got to
write the first thousand prime numbers
anybody going to the internet and
copying cutting and copying and pasting
code and using it as their own will be
thrown out for plagiarism but this is
one of the differences and once again at
the panel at a OSD this is something
Gregor express explicitly mentioned in
post-modernism the past is as part of a
present we have all the stuff that
everybody else has done and it's
available to us and we can use it and we
should use it and practically we must
use it because you know that's a
competitive advantage if we don't
somebody else doing that is going to
basically be able to out-compete any of
the efforts we might have so this is
where you know you find mashups coming
in this is where you find the scrapyard
system construction which basically says
you really have to go build your
system's bottom up from the components
that you are able to get that you're
able to beg that you're able to buy that
you're able to borrow and you probably
shouldn't steal them if they're
open-source I guess
so this you see shows one of the way in
which as well as if not replacing
modernism post-modernism can be seen as
fulfilling modernism the point is that
all this work Dijkstra doll Brad
Cox all the founding fathers and and
mothers adele goldberg Grace Hopper all
these great pioneers of our discipline
you know one of the things for example I
said was wouldn't it be great if we had
reusable components well the answer is
now we do have reusable components
wouldn't it be great if we had
high-level programming languages we do
have high-level programming languages
wouldn't it be great if you could build
a computer system that would safely fly
an aircraft from I don't know New
Zealand to Bonn and get you there in one
piece that was said as the grand
challenge at the software engineering
conference
in 1968 and if you look at Brian
Randall's discussion of this if you look
at Hugh Robertson 's discussion of where
software engineering that conference was
very important in setting if you like
the parameters and the worldview of
modern software engineering the point is
that we can the point is I wouldn't be
sitting in this hotel room today we
wouldn't be able to do this recording if
effectively all of those problems of
modern software engineering was solved
and so in some sense the question the
postmodern approach answer is ok now we
are in this new world now we do have all
these soft artifacts that are completely
available to us where does that leave us
how then should we develop software when
every program that needs to be written
has already been written how then should
we think about software what what are
these kind of problems that we need to
attack so ok I think we're more or less
running out of time since the bus for
the conference banquet will be going in
about 10 or 15 minutes anything else you
want to say for closing remarks on this
great paper and on this interview I was
talking earlier about how one of the
things with post-modernism is that there
are all these software components out
there and so nowadays if someone gives
you a program to write the first place
to start not the last place not after
you've done your design is to go out
onto the web or into a component
marketplace or some other of these
things the source code that you've
already got and find out what is
available and then beg or borrow or find
or buy the software components and use
those and kids don't steal software
components become a famous consultant
and they give you them for free ok so uh
that's it I guess or anything else well
thanks very much it's been it's been
great to be here on radio free software
engineering
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details